Faculty of Education fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
- Committee files, 1965 - 2000; F-233-3; 4.7 m of textual records 1 sound recording; Physical description: includes 4 audio cassettes (located in sub-series 3).
  - Savage Beagles / Management Meeting files, 1974 - 1987; F-233-3-12; 17 cm of textual records; Faculty of Education. Savage Beagles Meeting
    - Dicord meeting: agenda, minutes, supporting papers, vol. 2, 1986; F-233-3-12-0-13 (Archival box - standard 233-35)
    - Savage Beagles' meeting: agenda, minutes, supporting papers, vol. 1, 1987; F-233-3-12-0-14 (Archival box - standard 233-35)
    - Savage Beagles' meeting: agenda, minutes, supporting papers, vol. 2, 1987; F-233-3-12-0-15 (Archival box - standard 233-35)
  - Faculty Appointments Committee files, 1976 - 1977; F-233-3-13; 1 cm of textual records; Faculty of Education. Faculty Appointments Committee
    The Faculty of Education's Faculty Appointments Committee first appears in the record in 1976, but was likely already established by then, though not earlier than the 1972 faculty re-organization. It continues as of this writing (July 2008) as an active standing committee of the faculty. Its mandate is to review all candidates for appointment, arrange appropriate screening procedures, short-list candidates, and recommend candidates for appointment in accordance with university policies and procedures. Its composition has varied over time but includes the Dean or Associate Dean, Program Directors, and members elected by and from the faculty.
    Sub-series consists of one file relating to the activities and deliberations of the Faculty Appointments Committee. Records include correspondence, short-lists, and interview schedules.
    - Faculty Appointments Committee, 1976 - 1977; F-233-3-13-0-1 (Archival box - standard 233-32)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-3-5-0-3.
  - PDP Scholarship and Awards Committee files, 1979 - 1981; F-233-3-14; 1 cm of textual records; Faculty of Education. PDP Scholarship and Awards Committee
    The Faculty of Education's PDP Scholarship and Awards Committee first appears in the record in 1976, but was likely already established by then, though not earlier than the 1972 faculty re-organization. Its mandate is to advise the Director of Professional Programs on scholarships and awards, and to review applications and forward nominations to the appropriate Senate body. It continues as of this writing (July 2008) as an active committee.
    Sub-series consists of one file relating to the deliberations and activities of the PDP Scholarship and Awards Committee over a two-year period (1979-1981). Records include calls for nominations and list of nominees.
    - Faculty scholarships and awards, 1979 - 1981; F-233-3-14-0-1 (Archival box - standard 233-32)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-3-5-0-4.
  - Admissions Committee files, 1977 - 1987; F-233-3-15; 3 cm of textual records; Faculty of Education. Faculty Admissions Committee
    The administrative history of the Faculty of Education's Admissions Committee is not well-established. It was originally a sub-committee of the faculty's Professional Programs Committee and was established sometime between 1972 and 1976 to advise the Director of Professional Programs on student admission. In 1978 it became a standing committee of the faculty in its own right with a broadened mandate to consider and make recommendations to the faculty on all matters relating to admission of candidates to the PDP and Bachelor of Education degree programs; execute and monitor faculty and university polices and procedures regarding admission matters; and act as the first review level for admission candidates' appeals in the event of disputes. Membership consisted of the Chair (elected faculty member), the Dean, the Directors of Professional Programs and Undergraduate Programs, and individuals elected from faculty (two), PDP students (one) and faculty associates (one). The committee was dissolved some time between 1989 and 1994 (it appears on the annual "Committees of the Faculty of Education" lising in 1988-89, but not on the next extant one from 1994/95).
    Sub-series consists of records relating to the activities and deliberations of the Admissions Committee. Activities documented include policy development, application adjudication, intake review and analysis, and liaison with the Registrar's Office. Records include meeting agendas and minutes, reports, recommendations, guidelines, statistics, correspondence, notes and working papers. Note that there is a gap in the records, with no files surviving from 1981 to 1984.
    - Papers and correspondence, 1977 - 1980; F-233-3-15-0-1 (Archival box - standard 233-33)
    - Papers and correspondence, 1985 - 1986; F-233-3-15-0-2 (Archival box - standard 233-33)
    - Papers and correspondence, vol. 1, 1987; F-233-3-15-0-3 (Archival box - standard 233-45)
    - Papers and correspondence, vol. 2, 1987; F-233-3-15-0-4 (Archival box - standard 233-45)
- Centres and departments files, 1965 - 1973; F-233-4; 64 cm of textual records
  From 1965 to 1972 the Faculty of Education was organized into a number of separate centres and departments. This series represents the surviving records of these bodies.
  The series has been arranged into sub-series by the SFU Archives, based on the office of origin of the material. Each centre or department with surviving records has been assigned its own sub-series. Within each sub-series, files are arranged chronologically.
  A number of units that were originally part of a centre of the Faculty of Education subsequently became independent departments or moved to other faculties or administrative portfolios, and their early records will be found in other fonds. Examples include the Centre for Communications and the Arts (eventually became the School for the Contemporary Arts, see fonds F-109); the Communications program (became the School of Communication, see fonds F-92); the Kinesiology program (became the School of Kinesiology, see fonds F-60); and the Departments of Athletics and Recreation in the Physical Development Centre (became Recreational Services and Athletics, see fonds F-80).
  - Physical Development Centre files, 1965 - 1970; F-233-4-1; 1 cm of textual records; Physical Development Centre
    The Physcial Development Centre (PDC) was established in 1965 as one of the three original centres of the Faculty of Education. It was responsible for managing campus recreational faclities and intramural activities (Recreation Services); organizing SFU's competitive intercollegiate athletics program (Athletics); and offering courses relating to physical education through the university's General Education program. In 1967, the centre added the Department of Physical Development Studies to deliver courses on human growth and movement (kinesiology). Athletics and Recreatonal Services left the centre (and the Faculty of Education) in 1970 to become an independent administrative unit reporting to the Vice-President, Administration. The Faculty of Education as a whole re-organized in 1972, abolishing the PDC along with the other remaining centres, with Physical Development Studies moving to the newly established Faculty of Interdisciplinary Studies as the Department of Kinesiology.
    Sub-series consists of records made or received by the Physical Development Centre in the course of its operations. Activities documented include hiring, program development, and a review of the finances, organization and needs of the Department of Athletics and Recreational Services (1970). Records include correspondence, CVs and resumes, press releases, and reports.
    For other records relating to the PDC department, see the correspondence of the President and Vice-President, Academic in their respective fonds:
    - F-193, Office of the President fonds > Series 9-5, Professional Foundations (1965-1974): includes the President's correspondence with the Professional Foundations Centre.
    - F-220, Office of the VP Academic fonds > Series 3-2-2, Faculty of Education Centres (1968-1971): VP Academic's correspondence with each Centre and its departments.
    - Correspondence and releases, 1965 - 1970; F-233-4-1-0-1 (Archival box - standard 233-32)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-2-0-1.
  - Department of Behavioural Sciences Foundations files, 1965 - 1973; F-233-4-2; 39 cm of textual records; Department of Behavioural Science Foundations
    The Department of Behavioural Science Foundations (BSF) was established in 1965 as one of the original units belonging to the Educational Foundations Centre within the Faculty of Education. It delivered courses relating to theories of education, behaviour and cognitive development. With the re-organization of the Faculty of Education in 1972, the department merged with Communication Studies and left the faculty. This new body would become the Department of Communication Studies in the Faculty of Interdisciplinary Studies, established later that year.
    Sub-series consists of records made or received by the Head of the Department of Behavioural Science Foundations, R.J.C. Harper, in the course of administering the department. Activities documented include departmental planning (budget, enrollment, staffing, space); curriculum and program development (course planning, development of the Communication Studies program and establishment of the Department of Communication); student relations (enrollment, applications for graduate studies, registration and examinations); relations with faculty members (appointments, tenure, salaries); liaison with other university departments and participation in university, faculty and departmental committees; and liaison with external agencies and associations involved in education. Records include correspondence, reports, invitations, statistics and estimates; course proposals, outlines, and descriptions; and committee meeting agenda, minutes and supporting papers.
    For a list of the departments, committees, and external organizations represented in the correspondence and subject files, see the "Access points" section below.
    Calendar Committee (1965); Standing Committee on Data Processing; Ad Hoc Committee on Grading System; Space Allocation and Planning Committee. Arts and Education Sub-Committee; Faculty of Education. Curriculum Committee; Food Services Committee; University Salary and Promotions Committee; Committee on University Aesthetics; Joint Committee on Pensions; Department of Behavioural Scence Foundations. Departmental Tenure Committee; Office of the Bursar; University Bookstore; University Library; Physical Development Centre; Ancillary Services; Office of the President; Simon Fraser Student Society; Vancouver Counsellors' Conference; British Columbia Teachers' Federation; Canadian Association of University Teachers; Association of Universities and Colleges of Canada; Alberta Teachers' Association; British Columbia Principals' Conference; Burnaby Parent-Teacher Association; Canadian Association of Professors of Education; Canadian Mental Health Association; Ad Hoc Assessment Committee for Graduate Program in Communication; Simon Fraser University Staff Association
    For other records relating to the Behavioural Sciences Foundations department, see the correspondence in the fonds of both the President and the Vice-President, Academic:
    - F-193, Office of the President fonds > Series 9-5, Professional Foundations (1965-1974): includes the President's correspondence with the BSF.
    - F-200, Office of the Vice-President, Academic fonds > Series 3-2-7, Faculty of Education Centres (1968-1971): VP Academic's correspondence with each Centre and its departments.
    - Calendar Committee, 1965; F-233-4-2-0-1 (Archival box - standard 233-47)
    - Communications Centre, 1965; F-233-4-2-0-2 (Archival box - standard 233-47)
    - Educational Testing Services, 1965; F-233-4-2-0-3 (Archival box - standard 233-47)
    - Bookstore, 1965 - 1966; F-233-4-2-0-4 (Archival box - standard 233-47)
    - Standing Committee on Data Processing, 1965 - 1966; F-233-4-2-0-5 (Archival box - standard 233-47)
    - University enrolment estimates, 1965 - 1966; F-233-4-2-0-6 (Archival box - standard 233-47)
    - Vancouver Counsellors' Conference, 1965 - 1966; F-233-4-2-0-7 (Archival box - standard 233-47)
    - British Columbia Teachers Federation (BCTF), 1965 - 1967; F-233-4-2-0-8 (Archival box - standard 233-47)
    - Bursar, 1965 - 1967; F-233-4-2-0-9 (Archival box - standard 233-47)
    - Canadian Association of University Teachers (CAUT), 1965 - 1967; F-233-4-2-0-10 (Archival box - standard 233-47)
    - Graduate studies - faculty committees, 1965 - 1967; F-233-4-2-0-11 (Archival box - standard 233-47)
    - Graduate studies - inquiries, 1965 - 1967; F-233-4-2-0-12 (Archival box - standard 233-47)
    - Ad Hoc Committee on Grading System, 1966; F-233-4-2-0-13 (Archival box - standard 233-47)
    - Alberta Teachers' Association, 1966; F-233-4-2-0-14 (Archival box - standard 233-47)
    - Appointments, 1966; F-233-4-2-0-15 (Archival box - standard 233-47)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-5-0-2.
    - Arts and Education Subcommittee of the Space Usage Committee, 1966; F-233-4-2-0-16 (Archival box - standard 233-47)
    - Association of Universites and Colleges of Canada (AUCC), 1966; F-233-4-2-0-17 (Archival box - standard 233-47)
    - Behavioural Science Foundations, 1966; F-233-4-2-0-18 (Archival box - standard 233-47)
    - British Columbia Principals' Conference, 1966; F-233-4-2-0-19 (Archival box - standard 233-47)
    - Budget predications, summer 1966, F-233-4-2-0-20 (Archival box - standard 233-47)
    - Burnaby Parent-Teacher Association, 1966; F-233-4-2-0-21 (Archival box - standard 233-47)
    - Canadian Association of Professors of Education (CAPE), 1966; F-233-4-2-0-22 (Archival box - standard 233-47)
    - Canadian Mental Health Association, 1966; F-233-4-2-0-23 (Archival box - standard 233-47)
    - Curriculum Committee, 1966; F-233-4-2-0-24 (Archival box - standard 233-48)
    - Food Services Committee, 1966; F-233-4-2-0-25 (Archival box - standard 233-48)
    - Graduate studies, 1966; F-233-4-2-0-26 (Archival box - standard 233-48)
    - Librarian, 1966; F-233-4-2-0-27 (Archival box - standard 233-48)
    - Northern development research, 1966; F-233-4-2-0-28 (Archival box - standard 233-48)
    - Physical Development Centre, 1966; F-233-4-2-0-29 (Archival box - standard 233-48)
    - Registration and examination, 1966; F-233-4-2-0-30 (Archival box - standard 233-48)
    - Salaries, sabbaticals, tenure, 1966; F-233-4-2-0-31 (Archival box - standard 233-48)
    - University Committee on Salaries and Promotions, 1966; F-233-4-2-0-32 (Archival box - standard 233-48)
    - [Budget working papers], 1966 - 1967; F-233-4-2-0-33 (Archival box - standard 233-48)
    - Committee on Campus Aesthetics, 1966 - 1967; F-233-4-2-0-34 (Archival box - standard 233-48)
    - Faculty office requirements, 1966 - 1967; F-233-4-2-0-35 (Archival box - standard 233-48)
    - General, 1966 - 1967; F-233-4-2-0-36 (Archival box - standard 233-48)
    - General Services, 1966 - 1967; F-233-4-2-0-37 (Archival box - standard 233-48)
    - Graduate studies - applications, 1966 - 1967; F-233-4-2-0-38 (Archival box - standard 233-48)
    - Graduate studies - applications, refused, 1966 - 1967; F-233-4-2-0-39 (Archival box - standard 233-48)
    - Joint Committee on Pensions, 1966 - 1967; F-233-4-2-0-40 (Archival box - standard 233-48)
    - President, 1966 - 1967; F-233-4-2-0-41 (Archival box - standard 233-48)
    - Professional Development Program, 1966 - 1967; F-233-4-2-0-42 (Archival box - standard 233-48)
    - Regisrar, 1966 - 1967; F-233-4-2-0-43 (Archival box - standard 233-50)
    - Research vision, 1966 - 1967; F-233-4-2-0-44 (Archival box - standard 233-50)
    - Security, 1966 - 1967; F-233-4-2-0-45 (Archival box - standard 233-50)
    - Simon Fraser Student Society, 1966 - 1967; F-233-4-2-0-46 (Archival box - standard 233-50)
    - Staff Association, 1966 - 1967; F-233-4-2-0-47 (Archival box - standard 233-50)
    - University Committee on Appointment of Psychology Head, 1966 - 1967; F-233-4-2-0-48 (Archival box - standard 233-50)
    - Appointments, 1969; F-233-4-2-0-49 (Archival box - standard 233-50)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-5-0-16.
    - BSF Department Tenure Committee, vol. 1, 1969 - 1973; F-233-4-2-0-50 (Archival box - standard 233-50)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-5-0-8.
    - BSF Department Tenure Committee, vol. 2, 1969 - 1973; F-233-4-2-0-51 (Archival box - standard 233-50)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-5-0-10.
    - BSF Department Tenure Committee, vol. 3, 1969 - 1973; F-233-4-2-0-52 (Archival box - standard 233-50)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-5-0-12.
    - BSF Department Tenure Committee, vol. 4, 1969 - 1973; F-233-4-2-0-53 (Archival box - standard 233-50)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-5-0-14.
    - BSF Department Tenure Committee, vol. 5, 1969 - 1973; F-233-4-2-0-54 (Archival box - standard 233-50)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-5-0-15.
    - BSF meetings - minutes and papers, 1971 - 1972; F-233-4-2-0-55 (Archival box - standard 233-50)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-5-0-3.
    - Communications Studies - proposal and correspondence, vol. 1, 1971 - 1972; F-233-4-2-0-56 (Archival box - standard 233-50)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-5-0-4.
    - Communications Studies - proposal and correspondence, vol. 2, 1971 - 1972; F-233-4-2-0-57 (Archival box - standard 233-50)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-5-0-5.
    - Communications Studies - proposal and correspondence, vol. 3, 1971 - 1972; F-233-4-2-0-58 (Archival box - standard 233-51)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-5-0-6.
    - Chairman's correspondence, 1971 - 1973; F-233-4-2-0-59 (Archival box - standard 233-51)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-5-0-1.
    - Ad hoc assessment committee for graduate program in Communication, 1972; F-233-4-2-0-60 (Archival box - standard 233-51)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-5-0-7.
    - University Bookstore Committee, 1965 - 1966; F-233-4-2-0-61 (Archival box - standard 233-47)
  - Professional Development Centre files, 1966 - 1971; F-233-4-3; 11 cm of textual records; Professional Development Centre
    The Professional Development Centre has its origins in the Department of Professional Foundations, established in 1965 as one of the original units of the Educational Foundations Centre (EFC) within the Faculty of Education. As the faculty re-organized in 1970, Professional Foundations left the EFC to become a centre in its own right and was renamed the Professional Development Centre. From the outset, the department / centre was responsible for developing and delivering the Professional Development Program (PDP), the teacher training and certification component of the Faculty of Education at SFU. The centre was abolished in the 1972 re-structuring of the faculty, with the Professional Programs division established as its successor.
    Sub-series consists of records made or received by the Department of Professional Foundations / Professional Development Centre, and some of its committees. Activities documented include curriculum and program planning, policy development, student admissions, departmental meetings, departmental committees (admissions, tenure, program evaluation), liaison with other university departments and with external agencies and associations, participation in the Pacific Basin Economic Cooperation Council, and organization of the COLE conference in 1968 (Creation of a Learning Environment). Records include correspondence, reports, proposals, course outlines, studies, and meeting agendas and minutes. For a list of committees whose records are included in the files and other bodies represented in the correspondence, see the "Access points" section below.
    Professional Development Centre. Admissions Committee; Professional Development Centre. Departmental Tenure Committee; Professional Development Centre. Program Evaluation Committee; Pacific Basin Economic Cooperation Council
    For other records relating to the Professional Development Centre and the administration of the PDP program after the demise of the Centre, see the following series in this fonds:
    - F-233-3-7, Professional Programs Committee (1969-1986).
    - F-233-5-1, Professional Program files (1968-1997).
    - F-233-7-3, Professional Development Programs publications (1970-1999).
    - J.C. Patterson: Professional Development Program for Teachers - History and Rationale, 1966; F-233-4-3-0-1 (Archival box - standard 233-45)
    - Project reports, 1966 - 1967; F-233-4-3-0-2 (Archival box - standard 233-45)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-6-0-9.
    - Correspondence, 1966 - 1971; F-233-4-3-0-3 (Archival box - standard 233-45)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-6-0-4.
    - Department of Professional Foundations departmental meetings, 1967 - 1970; F-233-4-3-0-4 (Archival box - standard 233-45)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-6-0-2.
    - Pacific Basin Economic Cooperation Council, 1967 - 1971; F-233-4-3-0-5 (Archival box - standard 233-45)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-6-0-12.
    - Creation of a Learning Environment (COLE) - correspondence, 1968; F-233-4-3-0-6 (Archival box - standard 233-45)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-1-2-0-16.
    - Creation of a Learning Environment (COLE) - publicity, 1968; F-233-4-3-0-7 (Archival box - standard 233-45)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-1-2-0-17.
    - Professional Foundations Departmental Tenure committee - papers, 1968 - 1971; F-233-4-3-0-8 (Archival box - standard 233-45)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-6-0-6.
    - J.M. Greenwood: Background Factors of Successful and Unsuccessful Student Teachers at SFU, 1969; F-233-4-3-0-9 (Archival box - standard 233-45)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-2.
    - Correspondence, 1969 - 1971; F-233-4-3-0-10 (Archival box - standard 233-45)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-6-0-1.
    - Admissions - acceptance/rejection letters, 1970; F-233-4-3-0-11 (Archival box - standard 233-45)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-248.
    - Admissions Committee - format and procedures, 1970; F-233-4-3-0-12 (Archival box - standard 233-45)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-249.
    - Calendar of events, 1970; F-233-4-3-0-13 (Archival box - standard 233-45)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-6-0-11.
    - Interior and Vancouver Island faculty (orientation) meetings, 1970; F-233-4-3-0-14 (Archival box - standard 233-45)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-6-0-7.
    - PDP students, 1970; F-233-4-3-0-15 (Archival box - standard 233-45)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-6-0-8.
    - Policy statements, 1970; F-233-4-3-0-16 (Archival box - standard 233-45)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-247.
    - PDC meetings - agenda, minutes, supporting papers, 1971; F-233-4-3-0-17 (Archival box - standard 233-45)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-6-0-3.